<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bacterial Finches</title>
    <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Bacterial Finches</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Samuel Barreto</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 14:29:35 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://sam217pa.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Gospel of Greed</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/peirce-antide%CC%81terminisme/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 14:29:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/peirce-antide%CC%81terminisme/</guid>
      <description>Cet article correspond à ma traduction du paragraphe correspondant dans l&amp;rsquo;entrée Peirce de la Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy.
 C.S Peirce - Anti-déterminisme, Tychisme et Évolutionisme Contre les puissants courants du déterminisme qui dérivaient de la philosophie des lumières du XVIIIe siècle, Peirce insistait sur le fait qu&amp;rsquo;il n&amp;rsquo;y avait pas le moindre début de preuve scientifique pour le déterminisme et qu&amp;rsquo;en fait, il avait de considérables évidences contre lui.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Woese et Goldenfeld : la vie est physique</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/woese-goldenfeld-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Sep 2018 10:28:59 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/woese-goldenfeld-2011/</guid>
      <description>Ceci est une « traduction » encore une fois assez souple de l&amp;rsquo;article de Goldenfeld et Woese paru en 2011 &amp;mdash; l&amp;rsquo;un des derniers articles de Carl Woese.1 L&amp;rsquo;objet de l&amp;rsquo;article est de montrer que le phénomène vital ne peut être compris que comme émergent de phénomènes complexes et collectifs. Destiné à des physiciens &amp;mdash; l&amp;rsquo;article paraît dans Annual Review of Condensed Matter Physics &amp;mdash;, ils arguent que, tout comme les propriétés de la matière à l&amp;rsquo;état condensé ne sont pas réductibles aux propriétés des atomes qui la compose, le phénomène vital ne peut être réduit aux propriétés spécifiques de la matière sur laquelle il opère.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Le concept d&#39;information en biologie</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/information-biologique/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Sep 2018 15:08:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/information-biologique/</guid>
      <description>Ceci est une tradition relativement libre de l&amp;rsquo;entrée Biological Information de la Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy modifiée en 2016 par Peter Godfrey-Smith et Kim Sterelny.
Il manque ici des paragraphes entiers; je n&amp;rsquo;y ai pris que ce qui m&amp;rsquo;intéressait. (Je ne suis pas certain d&amp;rsquo;avoir le droit légal de traduire ça ici par ailleurs.)
 Le concept d&amp;rsquo;information a acquis un rôle dans de nombreux secteurs de la biologie.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Canguilhem, la connaissance de la vie</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/canguilhem-connaissance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 19:24:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/fr/canguilhem-connaissance/</guid>
      <description>L&amp;rsquo;Histoire des sciences montre que le concept de Vie est historiquement inscrit dans un processus que Canguilhem nomme oscillatoire entre des visions mécanistiques ou mécanicistes de la vie et des visions vitalistes.
Peu de praticiens de l&amp;rsquo;évolution tendraient aujourd&amp;rsquo;hui à avoir recours à cette vision vitaliste — la tendance actuelle étant au réductionnisme génétique. Elle est souvent rattachée à la description par Bergson de ce qu&amp;rsquo;il appelait « élan vital, » une conception de l&amp;rsquo;évolution orientée par ce que d&amp;rsquo;autres appelaient Entéléchie — notamment Driesch après Leibniz.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back To Blogging</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2018/08/08/back-to-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 18:22:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2018/08/08/back-to-blogging/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been eager to go back to blogging after more than a year of leaving it alone &amp;mdash; a PhD process is quite demanding, and I&amp;rsquo;m a father now … I always thought it was a pity that I stopped writing but here I am, trying to find some time to write again.
I&amp;rsquo;d like to apologize to readers I&amp;rsquo;ve not responded to, because of more pressing deadlines or stuff like that.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Removed Evil in ten points</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2017/01/31/why-i-removed-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2017 09:42:12 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2017/01/31/why-i-removed-evil/</guid>
      <description>Someone noticed in my recent init.el that I had removed Evil from my config. Here I want to explain why I grew frustrated with it.
To give you some context, I am an ex-vimmer that switched to Emacs initially out of curiosity for the Evil project. I tried to build my config using Evil before knowing any basic elisp, then learned about Spacemacs.
It was version 0.101 at that time if I remember correctly, so it was pretty mature already.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Context-dependent keybindings: a new emacs paradigm</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/10/18/context-dependent-keybindings/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 19:01:39 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/10/18/context-dependent-keybindings/</guid>
      <description>I recently discovered to use context dependent keybindings. Keypress that does different thing depending on where the cursor — the point — is in the buffer.
The idea is not new. I learned how to use it from this blog post by Arthur Malabarba. Lispy and Worf, two packages by abo-abo, use it everywhere.
Lispy uses the peculiar syntax of LISPs or LISPs-like languages to define keybindings that are aware of the context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keybindings strategies in Emacs</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/23/keybindings-strategies-in-emacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 19:23:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/23/keybindings-strategies-in-emacs/</guid>
      <description>Emacs is all keybindings. Escape Meta Alt Control Shift as they say. When you add another layer of possible keybindings with Evil, you end up being pretty limitless in your keybindings choices.
Here I want to describe how I bind keys in Emacs. I do this for two reasons: because writing helps me to formalise it, and to get feedbacks from you and your own keybindings strategies.
The outline is the following.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From helm, to ivy</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/13/from-helm-to-ivy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 19:02:47 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/13/from-helm-to-ivy/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I have seen a lot of Emacs users showing interest in Ivy. Most of them already know Helm or Ido. When someone asked Helm or Ivy? on reddit, I thought that I could give my opinion on Ivy, since I am an ex-Helm zealot.
Helm and Ivy are completion frameworks. It means they are tools that the Emacs ecosystem can use to narrow the field of possibilities after a given user input.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear weapon multi-editing via Ivy and Ag</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/11/nuclear-power-editing-via-ivy-and-ag/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2016 12:36:10 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/11/nuclear-power-editing-via-ivy-and-ag/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes when I am working on a project, I use project-wide variable or function definition. So I name them.
I usually suck at naming.
So when I think of a better name, I need a way to change it globally, ie in all the files of the current project that uses it.
In Spacemacs, I have heard of what Fabien Dubosson, one of the main Spacemacs dev, called the &amp;ldquo;nuclear weapon of multi-editing&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multilingual Hugo blog with GitHub Pages and Emacs</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/09/setup-a-multilingual-hugo-blog-with-emacs-and-github/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 14:29:08 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/09/setup-a-multilingual-hugo-blog-with-emacs-and-github/</guid>
      <description>Hugo is a great platform to deploy a blog with. Unfortunately and unlike Jekyll, I found it not very handy to setup a multilingual blog with. It has support for multilingual blog, but I think it is kind of hard to follow the guide.
So I decided to simply use git and git branches to build my blog with. And it works really well. If you are interested in building a multilingual blog with Hugo and GitHub Pages, please follow along.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to build your own spacemacs</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/02/how-to-build-your-own-spacemacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2016 21:29:21 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/02/how-to-build-your-own-spacemacs/</guid>
      <description>Emacs is a great environment to build a text editor. Being a really old piece of software, searching the internet does not always lead to the best or more recent results. My goal is to help you build an editor inside Emacs using the best tools for the job, with modern tools and well-crafted packages.
In a previous post, I described the tools I needed to build myself a great spacemacs-like1 experience inside emacs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrate iTerm2 in your Emacs setup</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/01/emacs-iterm-integration/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 17:48:38 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/09/01/emacs-iterm-integration/</guid>
      <description>The terminal experience inside emacs being what it is — ie really slow and kinda difficult to use —, I use iTerm2 as my main terminal. I put up three little emacs-lisp functions using AppleScript. They allow me to quickly switch between iTerm and spacemacs.
This one return the directory of the file currently opened. If it is a *scratch* buffer or something like that, it simply returns the home directory.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I build my own spacemacs</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/08/30/how-to-make-your-own-spacemacs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 17:57:03 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/08/30/how-to-make-your-own-spacemacs/</guid>
      <description>Spacemacs is a great starter kit. It is the only kit that got my attention. I have been using it for one year or so. I know most of its most useful commands. I like the plug-and-play feeling of its layer system. I like the laziness of its packaging system. I like how the devs build a great terminal experience inside emacs. I like how it abstracts Evil1 from its users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional Programming In R</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/07/05/functional-programming-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/07/05/functional-programming-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Functional programming is a style of programming which place the emphasis on functions. Functions helps to clearly express the intent of a piece of code. To me, R is a functional language. Its deep roots goes back to Scheme, a functional LISP dialect. The imperative part of R are to be found in its S legacy. In this post, I want to describe how I use functions in R, mixing imperative and purely functional programming.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>War of the languages</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/30/war-of-the-languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 12:52:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/30/war-of-the-languages/</guid>
      <description>Chosing a language I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to make up my mind about which programming languages I should know. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to the conclusion that I must know what matters to me. That&amp;rsquo;s not a very exciting conclusion.
But when you&amp;rsquo;re starting off in a new field, you are very curious about chosing the right tool for the job. You wander around on the internet, read some pros and cons of some particular language, start to learn about it, read some more pros and cons, switch to a new language, repeat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using LaTeX</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/07/using-latex/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 14:33:06 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/07/using-latex/</guid>
      <description>LaTeX is a great tool.
I&amp;rsquo;ve recently used it to write my master&amp;rsquo;s memoir (accessible here). I used Tikz to draw simple diagrams. They are really simple, yet I do not know of any other tool that I could use to produce these diagrams. In their first implementation, those diagrams integrated rather tightly text and figures. I said it before, and I say it again : I am firmly convinced that Tufte is right about integrating visual evidence with text.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Migrating to Hugo</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/06/switch-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 20:08:11 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/06/switch-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>I quit Jekyll today. Not a really huge decision to make, the blog is really small at this point. I could convert all metadata and all by hand. That was before I knew that Hugo has some tools to ease the switch.
So long Jekyll I got tired of Jekyll for two reasons. The first is that I had a lot of stuff to install before being able to serve and test my website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing my Emacs Paradigm</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/06/emacs-changing-paradigm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 19:47:05 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/06/06/emacs-changing-paradigm/</guid>
      <description>In my previous post, I talked about the way I tended to integrate everything in Emacs. In this one, I want to describe what lead me to totally change the way I use it.
Living in the terminal I just spend four months in front of my computer. I literally lived inside my terminal for various reasons. I had biological data to analyse, and software to develop to do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recombination and the evolution of base composition in prokaryotic genomes</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/project/projet-gbc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 16:44:43 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/project/projet-gbc/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s all the fuss about base composition ? Every genome is made of only four nucleotides : Adenine, Thymine, Guanine and Cytosine. By convention, biologists describe base composition of genomes in term of GC content, or GC%.
$$ GC\% = \frac{GC}{AT + GC} $$
Base composition is a fundamental genome trait. It typically varies many fold over the genome, and between genome. Since fifty years, microbial GC-content diversity has been described1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emacs in My Toolbox</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/02/06/2016-02-06-emacs-in-my-toolbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2016 15:42:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2016/02/06/2016-02-06-emacs-in-my-toolbox/</guid>
      <description>Emacs is a powerful tool. A frequent habit of emacs user is to try to migrate everything they know and use inside emacs. Emacs Gnus or mu4e, both emacs mail clients, emacs org-mode, a GTD mode inside emacs—which is actually extremely powerful—, emacs calc, a calculator inside emacs etc… are all attempts in this line of conduct.
As an emacs user myself, I also tried these stuff. And it works really well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lectures and Data Visualization</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/21/2015-10-21-lectures-and-datavis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 20:40:26 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/21/2015-10-21-lectures-and-datavis/</guid>
      <description>Powerpoints are everywhere. In our world of science, Powerpoints are the lingua franca of lectures. Yet they are seldom used to their rightful potential. I believe Powerpoints are often accused of the lecturer&amp;rsquo;s fault. I speak here with the legitimacy of a student that spent most of the last six years listening to lecturers with poor lecturing skills1.
I am a great admirer of Edward Tufte&amp;rsquo;s work about data visualization.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biased Gene Conversion</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/17/2015-10-17-biased-gene-conversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2015 15:17:18 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/17/2015-10-17-biased-gene-conversion/</guid>
      <description>Base composition of genomes is affected by many major process, being either neutral or selective. The neutral model describes mutations as following the genetic drift, which depends on population effective size. It does not represent the genome reality very well, but it is a useful model as a null hypothesis. One must reject the neutral hypothesis before affirming that a genomic trait is under selection constraints.
Natural Selection hypothesis  A curious aspect of the theory of evolution is that everybody thinks he understands it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hill-Robertson Effects</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/15/2015-10-15-hill-robertson-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2015 19:06:40 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/15/2015-10-15-hill-robertson-effects/</guid>
      <description>Hill-Robertson effects are interference between two locus under selection. When recombination is weak, selection on the two locus interfere. Selection is less efficient than when it acts on two independent locus.
 Consider A and B, two moderately advantageous allele, in different population. They are under positive or directional selection. If recombination is weak, an optimal AB combination can never appear. A and B interfere with each other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting a blog</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/14/2015-10-14-starting-a-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 16:38:14 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/2015/10/14/2015-10-14-starting-a-blog/</guid>
      <description>Following the advice of Andy Hunt, I decided to start a blog. I want to be able to communicate my ideas in the most limpid way. Being a non-native English speaker, it is crucial for me to get used to write in English.
Goal I am currently learning population genomics, applied to microbial communities. Me and my supervisors are studying a biased gene conversion process in bacteria, using a natural transformation model of recombination : Acinetobacter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/page/about/</guid>
      <description>I am a graduate student of the microbiology school of Lyon, France (see here). I am currently applying for a master thesis, under the supervision of Laurent Duret and Franck Bertolla.
I like Evolution, Microorganisms, Computers, Simplicity, Science, and Life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Samuel Barreto</title>
      <link>https://sam217pa.github.io/page/curriculum/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sam217pa.github.io/page/curriculum/</guid>
      <description>Who I Am  I am a passionate student of all things Evolution. I like when theories are adapted to facts I learn, and connect together. I like to think of Bacteria as the modern Darwin&#39;s finches, me being on a Genomic and Computerized Beagle.      What I Do  I study Microbiology and Evolution. I&#39;m currently focused on the biased gene conversion process, supervised by Laurent Duret and Franck Bertolla.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>